<sect1 id="chapter-cvs">
  <title id="title-cvs">Building GStreamer from CVS</title>
  <qandaset>

    <qandaentry>
      <question id="cvs-anon">
        <para>
How do I check out GStreamer from CVS ?
        </para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>
GStreamer is hosted on Freedesktop.org.  GStreamer consists of various parts.
In the beginning, you will be interested in the "gstreamer" module, containing
the core, and "gst-plugins", containing the basic set of plugins.
        </para>
        <para>
To check out the HEAD version of the core, use
<programlisting>
 cvs -d:pserver:anoncvs@cvs.freedesktop.org:/cvs/gstreamer co gstreamer
</programlisting>
This will create a directory "gstreamer" in your current directory.
If you want to get another module, replace the last "gstreamer" with the
name of the module.
        </para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question id="cvs-developer">
        <para>
How do I get developer access to GStreamer CVS ?
        </para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>
If you want to gain developer access to GStreamer CVS, you should ask for
it on the development lists, or ask one of the maintainers directly.
If you are not already a registered developer with a user account on
Freedesktop.org, You will then have to provide them with:
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>your desired unix username</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>your full name</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>your e-mail address</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>a copy of your public sshv2 identity.  If you do not have this yet, you can generate it by running "ssh-keygen -t dsa".  The resulting public key will be in .ssh/id_dsa.pub</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
        </para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>


    <qandaentry>
      <question id="autogen-libtool">
        <para>
I ran autogen.sh, but it fails with something like this:
<programlisting>
+ running aclocal -I m4 -I common/m4 ...
aclocal: configure.ac: 8: macro `AM_DISABLE_STATIC' not found in library
aclocal: configure.ac: 17: macro `AM_PROG_LIBTOOL' not found in library
aclocal failed
</programlisting>
What's wrong ?
        </para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>
aclocal is unable to find two macros installed by libtool in a file called
libtool.m4.  Normally this would indicate that you don't have libtool, but
that would mean autogen.sh would have failed on not finding libtool.
        </para>
        <para>
It is more likely that you installed automake (which provides aclocal) in
a different prefix than libtool.  You can check this by examining in what
prefix both aclocal and libtool are installed.
        </para>
        <para>
You can do three things to fix this :
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>install automake in the same prefix as libtool</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>force use of the automake installed in the same prefix as libtool
by using the --with-automake option</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>figure out what prefix libtool has been installed to and point
aclocal to the right location by running
<programlisting>
export ACLOCAL_FLAGS="-I $(prefix)/share/aclocal"
</programlisting>
where you replace prefix with the prefix where libtool was installed.
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
       </para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</sect1>
